Guide to the Rice University Anthropology Department records, 1957-2007 UA 234
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Anthropology Department records
1957-2007
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University. Department of Anthropology
UA 234
8 Linear Feet 16 boxes
These administrative files of the Rice University Anthropology Department reflect the daily business of the department, including correspondence, conference papers/articles/publications, CVs, research/travel funding requests, student evaluations, hiring and promotional materials, and personnel information. In addition, materials on anthropology syllabi and courses offered are included. This material begins in the 1950s and continues through 2007.
Biographical/Historical
Although the anthropology department was established at Rice University in 1961, its revitalization and redirection began in 1980. Because of its focus on high-quality, specialized, and creative work within the discipline during this decade, the anthropology department became well-known for both its identity and reputation. Such distinction became evident at the American Anthropological Association meeting in 1984, at which knowledge of Rice's accomplishments were widespread, and in the spring of 1986 when publishers bid vigorously for two volumes produced by Rice's anthropology department. At this time the anthropology department was on par with the small but specialized departments at Duke, Princeton, John Hopkins and Virginia, and the department's candidates were actively pursued by the large graduate departments of Harvard, Michigan, Chicago, and Stanford.
Traditionally the anthropology department was organized around a cultural anthropology core with archaeology and biological anthropology as additional tracks that supported the core. Since then, the social-cultural anthropology program has expanded and focuses on the application of anthropological methods and styles of research to the study of complex societies. Archaeology has become its own prominent track with emphases on the emergence of complex societies and urbanism, settlement studies, origins of food production, the Late Stone Age and Iron Age in Africa, and historical archaeology. Today the department of anthropology's doctoral program offers advanced training in these fields. In addition, students interested in medical anthropology have access to resources of the Texas Medical Center. The national prestige of the anthropology department at Rice continues to flourish.
Scope and Contents
These administrative files of the Rice University Anthropology Department reflect the daily business of the department, including correspondence, conference papers/articles/publications, CVs, research/travel funding requests, student evaluations, hiring and promotional materials, and personnel information. In addition, materials on anthropology syllabi and courses offered are included. This material begins in the 1950s and continues through 2007.
Faculty Files are restricted for privacy reasons, due to the inclusion of personnel information. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at woodson@rice.edu for assistance in accessing these materials.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research except for the Faculty Files, which contain personnel information. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at woodson@rice.edu for assistance in accessing these files.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to the Woodson Research Center in 2012.
Arrangement
This material has been arranged in three series, including Series I: Courses & Syllabi, Series II: Grants & Project Proposals, and Series III: Faculty Files. Series III: Faculty Files is divided into 7 subseries, all but one organized by the last names of faculty.
Index Terms
Subjects
Anthropology; Anthropology -- Japan; Universities and colleges
Document Types
memorandums; notes; reports; letters (correspondence)
- Series I: Courses & Syllabi, 1978-2007; 146080
  - Courses Offered, 1990-1992; 146081 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Courses Offered, 1992-1993; 146082 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Courses Offered, 1993-1994; 146083 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Courses Offered, 1994-1995; 146084 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Courses Offered, 1995-1996; 146085 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Courses Offered, 1996-1997; 146086 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Courses Offered, 1997-1998; 146087 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Courses Offered, 1998-1999; 146088 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Courses Offered, 1999-2000; 146089 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Courses Offered, 2003-2004; 146090 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Courses Offered, 2004-2005; 146091 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Courses Offered, 2005-2006; 146092 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Materials for General Announcements, 2006-2007; 146093 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - ANTH 201: Intro to Soc./Cult. Anthropology, 1978-1993; 146094 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - ANTH 308/508: History as Cultural Myth, 1982-1993; 146095 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - ANTH 327/527: Gender & Symbolism, 1981-1995; 146096 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - ANTH 333: Contemporary Trends in Social & Cultural Theory, 1985-1991; 146097 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - ANTH 341/351: Ethnographic Film in the 20th c., 1992; 146098 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - ANTH 367/567: Human Evolution, 1983-1994; 146099 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - ANTH 430/381: Medical Anthropology, 1980-1993; 146100 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - ANTH 446/646: Advanced Topics in Biomedical Anthropology, 1975-1994; 146101 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Anthropology Syllabi, 1978-1995; 146102 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Anthropology Syllabi Part II, 1977-1992; 146103 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Anthropology Syllabi Part III, 1979-1994; 146104 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Anthropology Syllabi Part IV, 1981-1996; 146105 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series II: Grants & Project Proposals, 1964-1992; 146106
  - Cushman, Richard D. Research Proposal & Projects, 1973-1975; 146170 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Cushman, Richard D. "Royal Chronicles of Ayutthaya" Project, 1977-1978; 146171 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Goodman, M.E. NIMH Proposal: "A Comparative Study of Cultures of Childhood,", 1969; 146109 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - LeCompte, D. Margaret Ford Foundation Project, 1987-1988; 146159 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Macken, Marlys NSF Final Project Report, 1989-1992, n.d.; 146110 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - McCord, William NIMH Grant, Sept. 1, 1965- Dec. 31, 1965; 146111 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - McCord, William NIMH Proposal, Jan. 1966- Jan. 1968; 146112 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - McCord, William NSF Research Proposal, 1965-1967; 146113 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - NSF Proposal: An Anthropological Study of Values and the Transmission of Values in "Successful" American Families, 1964 & 1969; 146107 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - NSF Systems Grant, 1967-1971; 146108 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Project Houston, 1965-1966; 146114 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Sheldon, Mary E. NSF Proposal, 1970-1971; 146115 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series III: Faculty Files, 1957-2003; 146116
  Scope and Contents note
  Contents include correspondence of faculty and administration as well as conference papers/articles/publications, CVs, research/travel funding requests, student evaluations, hiring and promotions, and personnel information. These files are under restriction due to private information. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at woodson@rice.edu for assistance in accessing these materials.
  - Last Names A - C, 146186
    - Adair, Linda S. Correspondence, 1979-1987; 146160 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Adair, Linda S. Curriculum Vitae & Ephemera, 1949-1982; 146163 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Adair, Linda S. Expenses, Forms & Reports, 1980-1988; 146161 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Adair, Linda S. Research Reports & Proposals, 1976-1978; 146117 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Arnold, Jeanne E., 1980-1985; 146162 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Ballonoff, Paul Alan, 1972-1975; 146164 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Colson, Anthony C., 1976-1977; 146165 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Creson, Daniel Lenard, 1970-1972; 146166 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Cushman, Richard D. Correspondence, 1974-1981, n.d.; 146168 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Cushman, Richard D. Files, Forms & Reports, 1974-1983, n.d.; 146169 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Cushman, Richard D. Promotional Materials, 1979; 146167 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Last Names D - H, 146187
    - Davidson, F. Chandler, 1969-1970, n.d.; 146172 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Davis, Philip W., 1966-1978; 146173 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Davis, Philip W., 1979-1987; 146174 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Davis, Philip W. & the Dept. of Political Science, 1977; 146175 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Engel, Frederic Andre, 1976-1977; 146176 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Fischer, Michael M.J., 1977-1993; 146177 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Gamst, Frederick C. Correspondence Part I, 1968-1971; 146178 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Gamst, Frederick C. Correspondence Part II, 1965-1975; 146179 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Goodman, Mary Ellen Correspondence, 1960-1970, n.d.; 146180 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Goodman, Mary Ellen Ephemera, 1957-1969, n.d.; 146181 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Goodman, Mary Ellen Special Copy Files Part I, 1967-1970; 146245 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Goodman, Mary Ellen Special Copy Files Part II, 1967-1970; 146246 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Harwood, Edwin (Sociologist) Correspondence, 1967-1970; 146182 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Hole, Frank, 1960-1961; 146183 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Hole, Frank, 1962-1978; 146184 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Hrdy, Sarah Blaffer, 1973-1981; 146185 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Last Names I - L, 146188
    - Ingham, John, 1967-1970; 146189 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Johnson, Gregory Alan, 1972; 146190 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Justice, Blair, 1965-1968; 146191 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Kaplan, Howard B., 1967-1968; 146192 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Karp, Ivan, 1984; 146193 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Kirkby, M.J. & Anne V., 1969; 146194 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Kolenda, Pauline Mahar, 1961-1963; 146195 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Lohse, Margie Chaffin, 1974-1977; 146196 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Lutfiyya, Abdulla M., 1967-1968; 146197 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Last Names M, 146200
    - Macken, Marlys Correspondence, 1990-1991; 146199 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Macken, Marlys Correspondence, 1992-1993; 146201 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Macken, Marlys Financial Papers, 1990-1993; 146202 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Macken, Marlys Status Reports/Research Account, 1990-1991; 146249 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Macken, Marlys Travel Expenses, 1991-1992; 146198 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Maranhao, Tulio P., 1981-1988; 146203 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Marcus, George Evaluations, 1975-1977; 146204 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Marcus, George Evaluations, 1978-1980; 146205 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Marcus, George Evaluations, 1981-1985; 146250 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Marcus, George Evaluations, 1986-1993; 146206 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Marcus, George Evaluations, 1994-2003; 146207 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Martin, William C., 1969-1970; 146208 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Milun, Kathryn, 1991-1994; 146210 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Milun, Kathryn, 1995-2000; 146209 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Last Names N - R, 146211
    - Neely, James, 1968; 146212 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Norbeck, Edward Correspondence Part I, 1961-1968; 146251 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Norbeck, Edward Correspondence Part II, 1968-1969; 146252 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Norbeck, Edward Correspondence Part III, 1970-1971; 146214 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Norbeck, Edward Correspondence Part IV, 1963-1981, 1991; 146213 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Norbeck, Edward Curriculum Vitae, n.d.; 146218 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Norbeck, Edward Ephemera, 1963-1974, n.d.; 146217 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Norbeck, Edward IIE, 1970-1971; 146216 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Norbeck, Edward Japan Trip, 1963-1968; 146215 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Pollitt, Ernesto, 1981-1986; 146219 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Price-Williams, Douglass, 1965; 146220 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Provencher, Ronald, 1967-1974; 146221 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Randolph, Richard R., 1962-1964; 146222 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Rasmussen, David Tab Correspondence, 1978-1988; 146223 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Rasmussen, David Tab Research Papers Part I, 1984-1988, n.d.; 146247 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Rasmussen, David Tab Research Papers Part II, 146248 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Last Names S - W, 146225
    - Sakumoto, Christine, 1968-1969; 146224 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Topazio, 1969-1971; 146226 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Traweek, Sharon Correspondence, 1984-1989; 146227 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Traweek, Sharon Correspondence, 1990-1993; 146228 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Traweek, Sharon Papers, 1985, 1987, n.d.; 146229 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Uzzell, John Douglas Correspondence, 1971-1979; 146230 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Uzzell, John Douglas Promotional Material, 1976-1977; 146231 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Uzzell, John Douglas Promotional Material Part II, 1976-1978; 146232 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Wagner, Erika, 1966; 146233 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Weiss, Kenneth Monrad, 1979-1983; 146234 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Wheeler, Wayne, 1959-1969; 146235 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - White, Leslie A., 1960-1970; 146236 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Other Anthropology Dept. Records, 146237
    - Research & Graduate Studies Correspondence, 1982-1992; 146238 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Research & Graduate Studies Correspondence, 1993-1995, 146239 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Faculty Correspondence, 1973-1975; 146242 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Frank Hole & Richard Blanton Correspondence & Papers, 1979-1979, n.d.; 146244 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Misc. Curriculum Vitae, n.d.; 146240 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Misc. Curriculum Vitae Part II, n.d.; 146241 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Promotions for Davis & Provencher, 1970-1973; 146243 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Russian ethnological maps of Near East, 1960 - 1962; 149047 (Box 16, Folder 6)